This video is about task 43.
This task is about drawing derivation trees.
We have been given a program here of two lines
–a Prolog program – and also a set of queries.
For each query we shall draw a derivation
tree and afterwards load the program in Prolog
using the trace command first and then step
through the computation using enter and semicolon.
And then reduce the output lines by just using
"Call" and "Redo" and each first "Fail" line.
Then we shall compare the output of
the protocol with our derivation tree.
Let's get started with the first
query and drawing the derivation tree.
This is the part of our first query.
Below we have the program for further reference.
In order to start the duration tree we
have to use each clause of the program.
We use unification steps on the clause
and each part of the program line.
In the first case we use the expression above
here and match it to mem(X, cons(X,Xs)).
We create the most general unifier for
it – matching mem, and x, and cons,
and then we have to match 2 to X
and to Xs we match cons(3, nil).
But first of all we rename the variables
in our expression here just to get
no duplications of variables – so to be
sure we rename all the variables here.
Now we do what i said right before – so we search
the most general unifier here for these variables.
Then we finally get that we replace
X and X_1 by 2 because X_1 has to match to 2 and
X_1 has to match to X so we replace both by 2.
Our Xs_1 has to be matched to con(3,nil),
that's also part of our most general unifier.
Now we take the most general
unifier and add it to our edge here.
We found an X here in in in this case which is 2.
This is a result we have
already because this is a fact.
So we are done in this case and we know that
we have found a variable X here and this is 2.
Now we continue with the second clause of our
program because we have just considered the
first clause here in this part of the tree
but we can also consider this part here.
We start again by doing unification of
this part and what's in our root
of the derivation tree – here.
Again we rename the variables.
So we rename by adding ones
here to have unique variables.
Now we do a unification of
those two expressions here.
We get a most general unifier for this again.
This time Y_1 is matched to 2 and X is matched
to X_1 and Xs_1 is matched to cons(3, nil).
We use this most general
unifier and add it to our edge.
At the next part of our branch – or on on
the leaf in this case at the moment – we
add the right hand side of our
expression that we just used.
Now we have mem(X,Xs) and we do the same
renaming as we did in the unification step.
So we replace the variables
here within mem to X_1 and Xs_1.
Now we apply the remaining part
of the most general unifier to
our expression here –
resulting in this expression.
This is the next part where we
start searching for the next edges.
And so we go through the program
again – using this expression.
This time we try to find the most
general unifier of those two.
So we search the most general unifier of
what's our leave now and the expression here.
This time we rename our variables again.
But we choose 2 as number – to not get in
conflict we just use the depth of our tree
as the number here, so we can be sure
that there is no overlapping of variables.
Now we find the most general
unifier for our expression.
Which will be X_2 replaced by 3, and X_2 has to
replace by X_1 as well so X_1 has to be 3 as well,
and Xs_2 is nil.
We add this most general
unifier again to our edge.
As this is a fact we have found a result.
This result is X=3.
We have done something else here because here
it's X_1 is tree, but when we write down the
result we also apply all the renamings backwards.
We have X_1 was X, that's why we say X=3 –
because X was renamed to X_1
and X_1 was then unified to 3.
And we know that X is the variable in the
original query – so that's why the result is X=3.
Now we go back to this part here.
We have to consider the other part
of our program – so the second line.
Again we have to do unification of the left-hand
side of the program line and our current query.
When we do this then we have to rename again.
Again we introduce variable
names here X_2, Y_2, and Xs_2.
We match the variables here in
order to get a most general unifier.
In this case X_1 is renamed to X_2,
Y_2 is matched to 3 and Xs_2 to nil.
We add this one again to an edge.
We have to consider the right
hand side of our query as well.
That's the next leaf here.
Again we do the renaming the same as
we did in our unification step here.
So we rename X and Xs to X_2 and Xs_2.
Then we apply the most general
unifier, which leads to mem(X_2, nil).
Now we try the same thing again.
We use this expression here and try to
match it to the first program clause.
This is the unification step of those two.
We do the renaming again so X_3, X_3, and Xs_3.
But we see that nil and cons are in conflict.
We cannot match those um those two expressions.
There is no most general unifier available.
Thus we cannot do anything
but try the next clause.
We do the same thing here try X to
unify with this left hand side here.
We do a renaming again so X_3, Y_3, and the Xs3.
Then we try to match this again.
We see it doesn't match as well as it did in the
other case – also because nil does
not match with cons(y_3, Xs_3).
There's no program line
left in our Prolog program.
Thus we know we have failed here
– so there's no further result.
Now we want to execute this stuff in Prolog.
This is the task again just in another format.
Here we have the queries written down.
This is the query that we
shall execute in our program in
Prolog and we use trace
before we execute the query.
Then we use enter and semicolon in
order to step through the whole process.
Let's load the program.
This is the program of Task43
– it's exactly this program.
We load it, use the trace command, and
I insert the query that we've seen here.
It's this query.
Now we can step through the whole process.
We can press enter in order to continue and
when we get a result we press semicolon.
And then again enter, enter, enter, enter,
semicolon, enter, enter, enter, enter, enter,
and then we are done.
Now we can
copy this whole path here and
place this into an editor.
We remove all the exit lines as it was
written in the task, and we also remove
all the failed lines except for the first one.
Now when we compare this to our tree
then we see – the first step some
sub call here with cons(2, cons(3, nil)).
That's the call of the program here.
So we try to match this one here.
And the result of this this is X=2
which is the case here as well.
Then there's a redo – so we step back
from here the starting point of the tree.
At the root again we have this second call here.
Then we get a result X=3.
This is the call here with 3
and nil three – so cons(3,nil).
There is now two left in this clause
here where the call is. Right?
Then we get X=3.
We step back and try to
match nil here in this case.
We have cons(3, nil) – that's that's this part
here – and then we step to the mismatch with nil.
Finally there is only left to do
the same steps for the other tasks.
So for um for mem(4, cons(2, cons(3,
nil))) and this other expression here.
These are more or less the same steps that we
have to execute so always try to um apply the
unifications until they fail.
When there's nothing left and so at each branch
every clause was tested then the tree is done.
And you can do so by just doing it yourself
it will help you practice this task and
the solutions are also available in the
collection so feel free to have a look there
but try to solve the tasks yourselves first.